<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short relation of the river Nile of its sourse and current, of its overflowing the Campagnia of Ægypt, till it runs into the Mediterranean, and of other curiosities / written by an eye-witnesse, who lived many years in the chief kingdoms of the Abyssine empire.</title>
            <title>Itinerário. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Lobo, Jerónimo, 1596?-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2733</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12438</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12254599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12254599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48869)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 154:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short relation of the river Nile of its sourse and current, of its overflowing the Campagnia of Ægypt, till it runs into the Mediterranean, and of other curiosities / written by an eye-witnesse, who lived many years in the chief kingdoms of the Abyssine empire.</title>
                  <title>Itinerário. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Lobo, Jerónimo, 1596?-1678.</author>
                  <author>Wyche, Peter, Sir, 1628-1699?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 105 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Martyn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation by Sir Peter Wyche of: Itinerario / J. Lobo.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Date palm --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Animals, Mythical --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prester John (Legendary character)</term>
               <term>Africa --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Nile River.</term>
               <term>Red Sea --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:57309:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb. 1668.</hi>
                  </date>
                  <hi>At a meeting of the Council of the Royal Society of</hi> London <hi>for Improving Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Knowledg.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Ordered</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe Diſcourſes, <hi>viz.</hi> A ſhort Relation of the River <hi>Nile,</hi> &amp;c. Of the <hi>Unicorne;</hi> Why the <hi>Abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine</hi> Emperour is called <hi>Preſter John</hi> of the <hi>Indyes;</hi> A tract of the Red Sea. Of Palme trees, Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of a Portugueſe Manuſcript at the deſire of the Royal Society, by <hi>Sr. Peter Wyche K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> fellow of the ſame, be printed by their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>BROUNKER</hi> Preſ.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57309:1"/>
            <p>A ſhort RELATION Of the RIVER NILE, Of its Sourſe and Current; <hi>Of its Overflowing the</hi> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagnia <hi>of</hi> AEGYPT, <hi>till it runs into the</hi> MEDITERRANEAN: And of other Curioſities:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by an Eye-witneſſe, who lived many years in the chief Kingdoms of the</hi> ABYSSINE EMPIRE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Martyn,</hi> Printer to the <hi>Royal Society</hi> and are to be Sold at the Sign of the <hi>Bell</hi> without <hi>Temple Bar,</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57309:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57309:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, HENRY L<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> ARLINGTON, one of the Lords of his MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTIES moſt Honourable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Councill; AND Principall Secretary of State.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE thoughtfull proviſion for my Journey, into <hi>Ruſſia</hi> (whither his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath been pleaſed to
<pb facs="tcp:57309:3"/>ſend me) hindered me from a more ſolemne Dedication of theſe Diſcourſes to Your Lordſhip: They were by Curious <hi>S<hi rend="sup">ir</hi> Robert South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> procured from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive and obſerving Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> who had lived many years in <hi>Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia</hi> and the <hi>Indies;</hi> ſo writ as to ſeem a candid Relation of matter of Fact, contai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a more precize and minut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> account of ſome Hiſtorica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Naturall Curioſities then is in any one Tract ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,
<pb facs="tcp:57309:3"/>and give the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueſe</hi> their juſt and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Title of Diſcovering dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>Weſt,</hi> the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Myſteries of the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> The <hi>Royal Society</hi> commanded me to Tranſlate them, and ordered the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. My Lord, Your benigne and encouraging Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, for all ſubtile and nice Enquiries; Your pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar province to get intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence from the <hi>South,</hi> and my particular obligations, countenance this Dedication,
<pb facs="tcp:57309:4"/>which (were I not in <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctu</hi>) the copious argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Your Lordſhips vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and perfections, would juſtly make much larger; now it muſt only excuſe the faults of the Tranſlation, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh my zeal of being eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt devoted Kinſman, and humble Servant; Peter Wyche</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57309:4"/>
            <head>A ſhort Relation Of the RIVER NILE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Emperour (vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly, though falſly called <hi>Presbyter John</hi> of the <hi>Indies</hi>) is Lord of the moſt ancient and largeſt Dominions of thoſe many Kingdoms and Provinces into which <hi>Africa</hi> is divided: This Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57309:5"/>is the moſt Eaſterly part of all <hi>Africa,</hi> called <hi>Ethiopia</hi> above <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> not without reaſon, all <hi>Egypt</hi> lying below it, and the ſame Situ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation have to it moſt of the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Red Sea</hi> bounds it on the Eaſt, <hi>Egypt</hi> on the North; On the Weſt, the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Africa,</hi> and on the South, the <hi>Indian-Sea;</hi> with this difference, that Eaſtward this Kingdom reacheth the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> though at preſent the <hi>Turks</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile its greatneſſe, by keeping the whole Shore of that Sea with two <hi>Forts</hi> in the <hi>Iſlands</hi> of <hi>Suaguem</hi> and <hi>Maſſuba</hi> and one upon the main Land called <hi>Arquico,</hi> which ſerves for no other uſe, than the defence of the Water drunck in the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Maſſuba,</hi> drawn out of Wells called <hi>Cacimbas</hi> ſunk near the head of a River, dry in the ſummer, full in the Winter, fetch'd daily in Boats called <hi>Geluas.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57309:5"/>
            <p>The <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Maſſuba</hi> and fort of <hi>Arquico</hi> are too leagues diſtant. This, the onely <hi>Port</hi> where is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported what <hi>Ethiopia</hi> wants, and whence the natural Commodities are exported, that, in circuit about twelve hundred fathoms; ſhap'd like a mans foot, hath a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Haven, little or no defence, though Gariſon'd by near ſixty <hi>Turks,</hi> white and black: The Cuſtomhouſe is inhabited by the <hi>Baſha's</hi> Lieutenant, (called <hi>Caqua</hi>) and other Officers.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Suaguem</hi> with the third Fort, is leſſe, but better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by Art and Nature, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with many Shoals, inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by an hundred <hi>Turks;</hi> being the reſidence of the <hi>Baſha</hi> out of the limits of the Empire, and of natural right belonging to a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull and warlike King, whoſe Kingdom is called <hi>Ballow,</hi> (anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently <hi>Negran</hi>) the Inhabitants are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57309:6"/>Moors, the Men, Horſes and Sheep the faireſt I have any where ſeen; the water-mellons the moſt delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous I have ever taſted.</p>
            <p>Toward the North, between <hi>Egypt</hi> and this Empire lies the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Deſart of <hi>Thebaide</hi> ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned for the ancient <hi>Ancorets,</hi> where begins the Kingdom of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> above mentioned.</p>
            <p>This Empire reacheth Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſo far into the main Land that the Kingdom of <hi>Congo</hi> was its tributary, as the great Hiſtorian <hi>John de Barros,</hi> affirmed in his firſt decade: At preſent it extends not further than the Kingdom of <hi>Naire</hi> whoſe Inhabitants are neither <hi>Abyſſines</hi> nor <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> yet not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in policy, garbe or govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: The ſoyle is rich in Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines of the ſame quality of thoſe of <hi>Sofalla,</hi> lying under the ſame parallel and not far diſtant, they pay a Tax yearly tribute of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57309:6"/>Gold to the <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Emperour, the Coyne called <hi>Miloqueas,</hi> the value ten thouſand pieces of Eight.</p>
            <p>The Greatneſſe of this Empire is toward the South more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd, there lying betwixt it and the Sea, divers Nations of Moors and Pagans, barbarous to extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which never did, nor do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg themſelves Vaſſals to the Emperour, who live in tents like the mountanous <hi>Africans.</hi> The chief amongſt them is elected every Eight year, with the Title of <hi>Caraye Primeyro</hi> afterwards cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Luba.</hi> The Moors bordering on the Sea-coaſt have Kings, the greateſt of them called <hi>Macheda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Empire anciently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded many Kingdoms and Provinces, their own Annals and ſome Hiſtorians count above twenty, with almoſt as many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces: What at preſent paſſeth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57309:7"/>for current; is, that its Greatneſs was notorious, though now limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to five Kingdoms, each about the bigneſs of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and to ſix Provinces, every one little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from<note n="*" place="margin">Two Provinces in <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Beyra</hi> or <hi>Alenteyo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of theſe, and among the biggeſt is called <hi>Agaos;</hi> the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the ſame name, whether theſe beſtowed their Name, or took it, from the Province. This is divided into Diverſe Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the moſt famous called <hi>Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cua,</hi> deſervedly glorious in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, being the Country of the famous <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne</hi> (of which I ſhall ſpeak in this diſcourſe, and onely now ſay tis not the <hi>Abbada</hi> (right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken by Authors for the <hi>Rhino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceros,</hi>) being in ſhape, a quite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Animal) and having in it the ſo long ſought for Head of <hi>Nile,</hi> concealed ſo many Age, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the induſtrious Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guees.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57309:7"/>
            <p>The higher part of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince is mountanous and woody, yet not without Vallyes and Groves of Cedars, for goodneſs and ſcent, not inferiour to thoſe of Mount <hi>Lebanus,</hi> their thickneſs is a great inconvenience to Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, but ſuites with the inclination of the native <hi>Agoas,</hi> who being profeſſedly <hi>Pagans</hi> and ſo of little faith or loyalty, live commonly in Rebellion, thereto invited, not more by their own natural diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition than the convenience of certain caves, into which in time of warr they retire, theſe Caverns have but one entrance, are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of one or two families, which are ordinarily great among the <hi>Pagans</hi> increaſed by their wives, multiplied proportionable to the Cows they keep, allowing to ten Cows one woman.</p>
            <p>What is moſt admirable in thoſe ſubterraneous Caves or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57309:8"/>is, that they receive not onely their Goods and Cattle (which are their whole Eſtates, perſonal and real, they living little on their crop) but they ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find in them water ſufficient to ſerve them the ſummer months, when onely they are aſſaulted, and are without apprehenſions of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conquered, though with ſmoak, by fire made at the mouth of the Cave, having Vents by which they receive ſufficient light, and can conveigh the ſmoak, if attempted by fire.</p>
            <p>In this Territory of <hi>Toncua</hi> is the known head and ſourſe of the River <hi>Nile,</hi> by the natives called <hi>Abani (i.e.)</hi> the Father of Waters, from the great collection it makes in the Kingdoms and Provinces through which it paſſeth; for the greateſt part of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> being mountanous, and the Torrents ſwel'd in the winter, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57309:8"/>ſo tranſmit them as to increas the Rivers, which falling into the <hi>Nile,</hi> make no little addition to its greatneſs, cauſing it to run with ſuch a ſtock of water as overflows the plain of <hi>Egypt:</hi> this is the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the Scripture in, <hi>Geneſis.</hi> 2. calleth <hi>Gihon,</hi> which encompaſſed the land of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> ſo doth <hi>Nile,</hi> with its turnings and Meanders.</p>
            <p>The Head riſes in the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Receſſe of the Territory, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving two Springs, called <hi>Eyes,</hi> each about the bigneſs of a Coach-wheel, diſtant twenty paces: The <hi>Pagan</hi> Inhabitants adore as an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol, the biggeſt, offering to it many Sacrifices of Cows which they kill there, flinging the head into the ſpring, eat the fleſh as holy, lay the bones together in a place deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for that purpoſe, which at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent make a conſiderable Hill, and would make it much bigger if carnivorous Beaſts and Birds of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57309:9"/>Prey did not by picking them, leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and ſcatter them.</p>
            <p>Theſe two ſprings riſe in a little field covered over with green and thick wood, Travellers, eſpecially Horſemen are eaſily convinc'd that this ground ſtands in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, from the trembling and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſound, this field is loſt in a Lake where 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der water.<note n="*" place="margin">Provincia ubi <hi>Nylus</hi> Oritur Vocatur <hi>Agaos,</hi> Vicina regno <hi>Gojam</hi> Terra vocatur <hi>Sagela,</hi> in apice montis in plano arboribus undiq, circundate. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</hi> Kercheri <hi>Oed. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt. Tom. 1. Cap. 7. p. 57.</hi>
                  <p>Fons <hi>Nyli</hi> ſitus in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate unius Vallis qua aſſimulatur ingenti cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po jugis montium undi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> circundato. ibi.</p>
               </note> This Plain is on the top of a high mountain, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looking many ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Vallies and from this hight inſenſibly deſcends; from the midle of this Deſcent is ſeen, near a Trench entangled with ſhrubs, the bigger of theſe ſprings whoſe bottom is not to be reached with a Lance of five and twenty palmes, which by the way meets with (as is gues'd) the roots
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57309:9"/>of the Neighbouring ſhrubs, ſo hinder'd further paſſage; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpring is to be fathom'd at ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Palmes.</p>
            <p>From the biggeſt ſpring runs in a ſtreight line a green and pleaſant Wood ſeeming to follow the courſe of the water, which though under ground, leaves the veine to be track'd by its re-appearing at the diſtance of little more than an hundred paces, at this appearance the quantity of water is ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, as onely to make a very little Rivulet, which grows preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bigger, by the aſſiſtance of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſprings bringing in their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. At little more than three dayes journey from the Head, the River is large, deep enough for Veſſels to ſail in, and ſo broad that I doubt whether a ſtrong arm can throw a ſtone over it.</p>
            <p>A little above a hundred paces from this place, this River ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veys
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57309:10"/>it ſelf betwixt rocks, as in the year 1629. I paſſed it without wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my foot; in my journey from the Kingdom of <hi>Gojama</hi> to the Province of <hi>Dambeha</hi> when, the Paſſengers being many; and the Boats but few (which I will anon deſcribe) I with my companions going along the banks of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and engaged among many little Rivulets, leaping from ſtone to ſtone, got dry to the other ſide; the ſame did immediately many others, naming it the Paſſage of Father <hi>Jeronimo,</hi> I being the firſt who diſcovered or attempted it.</p>
            <p>This is the ordinary paſſage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Nile</hi> moſt frequented by Travellers, who come from the Court and Province of <hi>Dambeha</hi> for the Kingdom of <hi>Gojama,</hi> the Territory called <hi>Bed,</hi> the paſſage over in Boats with head and Sterne, made of groſſe and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57309:10"/>thick<note n="*" place="margin">Navigatio hic nulla niſi cymbis papyraceis quas ipſi Tancoas appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. <hi>Voſſius</hi> de Origine <hi>Nili, Cap. 16. p. 55.</hi>
                  <p>Conficitur bibulâ Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitis Cymba papyro. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> matt, ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyned and put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether yet not ſecure from falling in pieces, which often happens and the Paſſengers left in the water; they are rowed with long round poles, being without the uſe or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any other Oars; are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of receiving about ten per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with ſome baggage, many ſwim over; ſo do all the beaſts, and both man and beaſt go in danger of ſome mortall accident from the Sea-horſes and Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles, both bred in the <hi>Nile,</hi> and infeſting the paſſages.</p>
            <p>From this place the <hi>Nile</hi> grows crooked, making almoſt a ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circle: Two dayes journey from this paſſage it runs by a point of land into a Lake of freſh water called by the Natives <hi>Dambeha,</hi> abounding with wild-foul, ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57309:11"/>there is, but little fiſh, the reaſon conceived that the Sea-Horſes fright, and the <hi>Crocodiles</hi> devour them, this Sea is in length twenty five leagues, fifteen over at the largeſt place, about the middle are divers <hi>Iſlands</hi> of different big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, full of Wood, ſome inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, others deſart: The biggeſt called <hi>Dec,</hi> two leagues long, but narrow, hither are baniſhed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned perſons ſent for ſecurity, whereas the Boats not being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and pain of death to any who without leave go to the <hi>Iſland,</hi> all means of eſcape is deſperate, ſwimming is leſſe inviting, the Lake being full of Sea-horſes and <hi>Crocodiles,</hi> which to meet is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain death.</p>
            <p>The point of this Lake is with ſo much violence broken by the <hi>Nile,</hi> that the current is divided in the water and Mud till it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a paſſage at another place.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57309:11"/>The <hi>Nile</hi> is for about a quarter of a league detained in this Lake, leaving that, it makes a beautifull and large Tour, ſo great, as to contain in the circumference a Kingdome call'd <hi>Gojama</hi> about the bigneſſe of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and a great part of another call'd <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes.</hi> By this circuit the <hi>Nile</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns again within leſſe than two dayes journey of its head; hence taking a ſouth eaſt courſe run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning through many Kingdoms and Provinces, it falls into <hi>Egypt,</hi> by the way in diverſe places are made thoſe ſo canazing and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Cataracts, ſo famous for their noyſe, when the water fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with its whole Body ſinks and hollows the <hi>Abyſſe</hi> which receives it. Yet doth not the greatneſſe of the noyſe deafen the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inhabitants, as ſome fabulouſly write, if ſo, the populouſneſſe of the adjacent places would ſwarm
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57309:12"/>with deaf multitudes, which hear the noyſe and find not that effect. One of theſe Cataracts is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently remarkable, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the relation of what hath ſurpriz'd and allured many.</p>
            <p>At the firſt or ſecond Cataract the <hi>Nile</hi> makes; The water from an high and craggy rock is praec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated with all its maſſe into a large and deep <hi>Abyſſe,</hi> the noyſe heard three long leagues, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rebound, (which ſpends it ſelf i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> minute atomes and ſubtile ſmoak ſeen as farr. The water to adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration being ſhot with ſo muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Violence as to fall at a diſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> makes an arch, and under that leaves a larg Road where peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paſſe, in ſecurity not to be we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> There are convenient ſeats cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out in the Rock for Travellers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſt themſelves, where they enjo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the moſt pleaſant ſight Imagin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can fancy, made by the ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57309:12"/>reflection on the water, ſo produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing glorious and pleaſing Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, reſembling thoſe of the Rainbow, which at this nearneſſe of the water, moſt deliciouſly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy and feaſt the Eye.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Nile</hi> was never under any Bridg, before we arrived in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia;</hi> The firſt made in the Kingdom of <hi>Amara,</hi> where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two high Rocks was a ſtreight and dangerous paſſage: The <hi>Nile</hi> ran deep and violent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, all ran great hazzard, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loſt in the paſſage, the winter chiefly increaſed the difficulty; The <hi>Abyſſines</hi> were incapable of removing this evil, ignorant what Bridges were, and without Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to make them: The Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, informed what a Bridge was, how conveniently made in ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Paſſage, and we having brought from <hi>India,</hi> in the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arks company, two ſtone-cutters,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57309:13"/>deſigned for building Churches in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> One was recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this work, who made this firſt Bridg, of a beautifull ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture and great convenience to Paſſengers: Thus was the <hi>Nile</hi> at firſt brought under a ſtrange Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion.</p>
            <p>This diſcourſe is not improper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ended, by a reflection why an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great and <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> uſing ſo great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to diſcover the head of <hi>Nile,</hi> miſcarried in the Enterprize: The reaſon was, becauſe they ſent diſcoverers againſt the ſtream: Thus going by Land, the length of the journey, the many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Provinces to be travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led through, the ſwarms of Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people to be incountred, ſo many unwholeſom Clymates to be paſs'd, made their advance im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; going by water, the ſame difficulties increas'd, attend them:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57309:13"/>The violent Current of <hi>Nile</hi> ſtopt their paſſage, and coming to the firſt Cataract, they could not proceed, but were forced back with loſt Labour; and being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either knowledge of, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Empire by the Red ſea, they neither ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured that way, nor conceived their deſigne ſo feiſible. Thus were their endeavours fruſtrated; the knowledg of this Province would, by ſome of the <hi>Ports</hi> of the Red ſea, have brought them into the <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Empire, thence two months journey had made them drink in this ſo deſirable, ſo concealed, and ſo famous Spring. This ſecret, (with divers others of many parts of the world, and their diſcovery) was received for the indefatigable induſtry of the <hi>Portuguees,</hi> who have ſeen with their Eyes, what many have deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but could not obtaine.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57309:14"/>
               <head>The true Cauſe of the River <hi>Nile</hi>'s overflowing and drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Campagnia of <hi>Egypt</hi> at the heighth of Summer in <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DIvers cauſes were by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients aſſigned, for the <hi>Nile's</hi> overflowing in the hotteſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer months in <hi>Europe,</hi> according to the Opinion of the Writers, every one aſſerted what was in the reach of his reaſon, yet all wandred from the truth. The little knowledge had of the ſourſe and current of this ſo famous Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, of the places it paſſeth through, and chiefly of the inland of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> where it riſeth, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ſuch variety of Opinions, without the diſcovery of the truth reſerved for the Navigation and Commerce of the <hi>Portuguees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The great quantity of Snow,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57309:14"/>which falls in the rigour of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on the inland mountains of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> and is melted by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe heat of the Summer, is not, as ſome affirme, the cauſe of this Rivers overflowing; <hi>Ethiopia</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not ſo ſharp colds as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Snow, unknown in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, nor conceivable from our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: Two Places onely have a thick white Froſt, and Haile in great quantities, which reſemble, but are not, Snow; One is in the Kingdom of <hi>Tigre,</hi> upon the high mountains of <hi>Seman,</hi> the other in the Kingdom of <hi>Damotis,</hi> in the Territory called <hi>Namora</hi> of the cold Climate, which melted, do ſuperficially water the mountains, therefore miſtaken for Snow, ſemetimes fall with a Current in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the low-lands, yet not ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably, as to ſwell the Rivers, much leſſe to cauſe the innundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Nile.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57309:15"/>
               <p>Neither do the great Winds, which in thoſe months of the overflowing of <hi>Nile,</hi> blow in at the mouth of the River, where it runs into the Mediterranean, cauſe this Innundation; as others aſſert, who ſay, thoſe winds repell the water, which being detained, with the water which deſcends, increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to that Exceſſe, to force the <hi>Nile</hi> out of its Channel, and ſtagnate in the Plains of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſo enriching and fatning the ſoyle, by the ſlyme brought from thoſe places through which it paſſeth.</p>
               <p>Other reaſons, of the ſame cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, given by Authors, I omitt, in haſt to declare the true one, onely attainable by ſuch who have lived ſome years in <hi>Ethiopia.</hi> The truth in ſhort, is, that, the winter in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> is the ſame and at the ſame time, as in <hi>India,</hi> and other places under the <hi>Torrid Zone,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at the end of <hi>May,</hi> or the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57309:15"/>firſt days of <hi>June,</hi> and in all <hi>Auguſt</hi> (the reaſon of the faireſt weather in <hi>Europe</hi>) ſpends its greateſt fury; the overflowing of <hi>Nile,</hi> being at the height in theſe months, the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of Summers and Winters begat the Opinions mentioned: Whereas, the greateſt part of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia</hi> being mountanous, and the <hi>Nile</hi> in its courſe through many Kingdoms and Provinces of the Inland, collecting the Rain wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which fall from the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and receiving into it many great Rivers, thus becomes ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable and maſterleſſe: As the plain of * <hi>Egypt</hi> experimentally and to its great benefit finds.<note place="margin">—Nihil indiga mercis Aut jovis in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo tanta est fiducia <hi>Nilo.</hi>
                  </note> As much diſcountenanced by the Heavens, in being deprived of the common benefit of Rain, as mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificently requited by the water of this famous River, which gave riſe to the obſervation, That the <hi>Egyptians</hi> never lift up their Eyes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57309:16"/>to Heaven, never expect any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from God Almighty, but wholly depend upon the <hi>Nile;</hi> thence receiving that benefit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places enjoy by Rain; thoſe Verſes of <hi>Ovid,</hi> may ſeem not Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to the <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Os homini ſublime dedit, coelum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> videre</l>
                  <l>Juſſit, et erectos ad ſydera tollere vultus</l>
               </q>
               <p>The <hi>Nile,</hi> running into the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterranean, waſheth the Walls of <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> diſtant from the mouth fifty miles. This River de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth by the way, the more or leſs abundance to be expected that year; The Harveſt, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the greater or leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation, is thus concluded. The Walls of this populous City have to ward the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<note n="*" place="margin">The Author, a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Eye-witneſſe of all he relates, and ſo of undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Credit, took this onely thing upon report that the <hi>Nile</hi> waſheth the walls of <hi>Gran-Cairo,</hi> and that on the inſide of this Tower in the walls, ſhould be kept the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gister of the innundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Nile,</hi> which is on a Marble Pillar, placed in the middle of the River, near a long <hi>Iſland</hi> called <hi>Rhodes</hi> oppoſite to <hi>Gran Cairo;</hi> upon this <hi>Iſland</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Pillar is built a <hi>Moſque,</hi> with ſuch an Arch towards the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to give the water paſſage. This place and Pillar is ſo ſuperstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſecured from the ſight of Christians, that I found the attempt vain and dangerous; onely ſaw in <hi>January</hi> the bottome of the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in the water: The other Circumstance of the number of Degrees and the Proclamation, are truly related.</note> a Tower open with an Arch giving paſſage to the <hi>Nile,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57309:16"/>which according to the waters it brings down, riſeth more or leſs. On the walls of this <hi>Tower</hi> are from the bottome upward, made marks, or degrees, and by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cuſtome, as more or fewer of theſe are covered with water, the Magiſtrates make it be proclaimed every night in the ſtreets that the knowledge how many degrees the <hi>Nile</hi> hath that day overflowed may be general. This Proclamation begins at the end of <hi>July,</hi> and continues all <hi>Auguſt,</hi> when the riſe or fall of the River is Particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved by the degrees. The abundance of the year is thus gueſſed at, when the water covers
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57309:17"/>not ſixteen degrees the want of water ſuggeſts fear of a Famine; riſing towards twenty five, the higher it aſcends, the fairer are the hopes of a fruitfull ſeaſon; paſſing that number, they are aſſaulted with new fears of death, the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of water not allowing them to ſow, or houſe their Harveſt. Theſe months paſſe not away, without ſome trouble and anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the weather being every where ſubject to irregularity, ſo rain is ſometimes too much, ſometimes too little, by which the Crop is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</p>
               <p>Another Curioſity makes the <hi>Nile</hi> famous, whoſe current ſtores <hi>Gran Cairo</hi> with Senna ſo known, and ſo experienced in Medicine in the ſhops of <hi>Europe;</hi> It is a little ſhrub peculiar onely to the woods of <hi>Ethiopia:</hi> the place where I li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in that Kingdom hath great quantity. The Wild <hi>Negro's</hi> fetch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57309:17"/>it from the Inland, and bring it in great Boats to <hi>Grand Cairo.</hi> The French Conſul there hath the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoly of it, for which he preſents every new <hi>Basſhaw</hi> with thirty thouſand Dollars, and bargains at a certain ſet price and a day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixt, to buy all that comes; which he performs Having houſed it in his Magazines, he divides it into three parts two are burnt, one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be tranſported for <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> which payes for the two parts conſumed: There is leſs Expence for fraight, the Shops alwayes want the Medicine which goes off at the price demanded: Thus is the account ballanced, a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Zacharias Vermiel,</hi> a ſervant many years in the Conſul's houſe, gave me this Information, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to travell, brought him by Land into <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> where he lived a year in my houſe, and when we were baniſhed, went into the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57309:18"/>army, being grown rich, and turn'd Inhabitant, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to returne, he died there, ten years after his arrival.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the famous <hi>Unicorne,</hi> where he is bred, and how ſhap'd.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn</hi> is the moſt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated among Beaſts, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Birds are the <hi>Phaenix,</hi> the <hi>Pellican</hi> and the Bird of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice:</hi> with which the world is better acquainted by the fancies of Preachers and Poets, than with their native ſoyle; little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is of any of them, for ſome of them, nothing but the received report, of their being in nature; it deſerves reflection, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and indefatigable labour of men in the diſcovery of things concealed, can yet give no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count where the <hi>Phaenix</hi> and Bird
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57309:18"/>of Paradiſe are bred: ſome would have <hi>Arabia</hi> the Country of the <hi>Phaenix,</hi> yet are the <hi>Arabians</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any knowledge of it, and leave the diſcovery to the work of time. The Bird of Paradiſe is found dead with her Bill fixt in the ground, in an <hi>Iſland</hi> joyning to the <hi>Mallucco's</hi> not far from <hi>Macaca,</hi> whence it comes thither, unknown, though great diligence hath been imployed in the ſearch, but without ſucceſſe: One of them dead came to my hands. I have ſeen many, the Tayle is worn by Children for a Penaſhe, the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fine and ſubtile as a very thin cloud; the body not fleſhy, reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling that of a Thruſh; the many and long feathers (of a pale invivid colour, nearer White than Aſh-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour) which cover it, make it of great beauty. Report ſaies of theſe Birds, that they alwayes fly, from their birth to their death, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57309:19"/>to have any feet; they live by flyes they catch in the Air, where, their diet being ſlender, they take ſome little repoſe, they fly very high, and come falling down with their wings diſplayed; As to their Generation, Nature is ſaid to have made a hole in the back of the Male, where the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male laies her Eges, hatcheth her young and feeds them till able to fly: great trouble and affection of the Parent. This is on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Authors credit which gives the relation; I ſet down what I have heard. This is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Bird ſo lively drawn in our Maps.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pellican</hi> hath better credit (called by <hi>Quevedo</hi> the ſelf dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plining Bird) and hath been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in the land of <hi>Angola,</hi> where ſome were taken; I have ſeen two. Some will have a Scar in the breſt, from a wound of her
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57309:19"/>own making there, to feed (as is reported) her young with her own bloud, an action which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily ſuggeſts devout fancies. So much of Birds. Among Beaſts we come to the famous <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne,</hi> of the more credit, becauſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in holy Scripture, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to many things,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Edie vulg.</hi> Pſal. 28. vers. 6.</note> even to God made man. None of the Authors, who ſpeak of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne</hi> diſcourſe of his birth or Country, ſatisfied with the deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Elodiums, by which he is cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated. That ſecret reſerved for thoſe who travell'd and ſurvey'd many Countries.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne</hi> is not to be confounded with the <hi>Abada</hi> (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly contended for) is certain, from the difference of the names of <hi>Rhinoceros</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne</hi> not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably to be given to both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction, and from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of their Bodies and parts; as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57309:20"/>appears in the <hi>Abada</hi> we know, and in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne</hi> we ſee pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. This has one great ſtraight horne, of admirable virtue, the <hi>Abada</hi> or <hi>Rhinoceros</hi> hath two, a little crooked, not ſo Soveraigne, though uſed againſt poyſon. The Country of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne</hi> (an <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> creature, onely known there) is the Province of <hi>Agaos</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Damotes;</hi> that it may wander into places more remote is not improbable: This Animal is as large as a handſome horſe, of a dark brown colour, with the mane and tayle black, both ſhort and thin (though in other places of the ſame Province they have been obſerved with them longer and thicker) with a fair beautifull horne, in the forehead, five palms long, as is painted, the colour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to white: they live in cloſe woods and Thickers, ſometimes venture into the Champian, not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57309:20"/>often ſeen, being timerous, are not many, and thoſe concealed in the Woods; The moſt barbarous and ſalvage people the world hath, enjoy them and probably feed upon them as upon other Beaſts.</p>
               <p>A Father, my Companion, who ſpent ſome time in this Province, upon notice that this ſo famous Animal was there, uſed all poſſible diligence to procure one; the Natives brought him a very young Colt, ſo tender as in few dayes it died. A <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, a perſon of years and credit reſpected by all his acquaintance, and of great eſteem with ſome Princes of that Empire, under whom he had ſerved, gave me this relation of the great ones: He told me, that returning once from the Army (whither he uſually went every Summer with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Malac-Segued</hi>) with twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57309:21"/>other <hi>Portugueſe</hi> ſouldiers in company, they one morning reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a little valley encompaſſed with thick woods, deſigning to breakfaſt, while their horſes gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed on the good graſſe which plentifully grew there, ſcarce were they ſate down, when from the thickeſt part of the wood, lightly ſprang a perfect horſe of the ſame colour, hair and ſhape before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; his carrier was ſo brisk and wanton, that he took no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of thoſe new inmates, till in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged amongſt them; then as frighted at what he had ſeen, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſtarted back again, yet left the ſpectators ſufficient time to ſee and obſerve at their pleaſure. The particular ſurvey of his parts ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them with delight and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, one of his ſingularities was, a beautifull ſtreight horne on his forehead, like that above mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; he appear'd to run about
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57309:21"/>with Eyes full of fear; our horſes ſeem'd to allow him for one of the ſame brood, curveted and made towards him; the Souldiers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving him in leſſe than Musket ſhot, not able to ſhoot, their mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets being unfixt, endeavoured to encompaſſe him, out of an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that that was the famous <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne</hi> ſo often ſpoken of, but he prevented them, for perceiving them, with the ſame violent car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier he recovered the wood, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> ſatisfied in the truth of ſuch an Animal, diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented at the loſſe of their Prize. My knowledge of this Captain, makes the truth with me undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>In another Place of the ſame Province, (the moſt remote crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and mountanous part call'd <hi>Nanina</hi>) the ſame Beaſt hath been often ſeen, grazing amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of different kinds. This
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57309:22"/>place is in the furtheſt receſſe of the Province, therefore the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary place of baniſhment for thoſe the Emperour intends to keep ſecurely; it ends in high mountains which overlook great and vaſt Plains, and Forreſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by ſeveral ſorts of wild beaſts: To this place of baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a Tyrannical Emperour, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Adamas-Segued</hi> ſent without any cauſe divers Portugueſes, who from the top of theſe mountains, ſaw the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicornes</hi> graze in the Plains below, the diſtance not greater than allowed them ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct an Obſervation, as they knew him like a beautifull Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net with a fair horne in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. Theſe teſtimonies, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly that of the good old man <hi>John Gabriel,</hi> with what the Father, my Companion, affirmed of his own knowledge, confirmes me, that this ſo celebrated <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne,</hi> is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57309:22"/>in this Province, there foaled, and bred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Reaſon why the <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Emperour is called <hi>Preſter John</hi> of the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat there was anciently in the Eaſt-Indies a puiſſant Chriſtian Prince, Lord of many Kingdoms and large Territories, is out of queſtion: being groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the authentick authority of good Hiſtorians and Authors; as undoubted is it, that at preſent there is no ſuch Prince; his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory periſhed many ages ſince, leaving the extent of his Empire undecided. Both theſe Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are proved by the famous Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian <hi>John de Barros</hi> in his Decads. And the advance made by the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> into the <hi>Indies,</hi> aſſures us, that at preſent no ſuch Prince
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57309:23"/>is known in thoſe many Kingdoms and Provinces of the Eaſt, by them diſcovered.</p>
               <p>This being out of controverſy, yet the Emperour of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> in the opinion of many, paſſeth for that famous <hi>Presbyter John</hi> of the <hi>Indies;</hi> by this name commonly, though falſly called, by thoſe who pretend much, but have little knowledg of him.</p>
               <p>There have not been wanting ſome late Authors, who upon ſmall grounds, and leſſe truth, would maintain this opinion and report, proving by divers Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies and interpretations of the word, that the <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Emperour was properly <hi>Preſter John:</hi> But this affirmation being without any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of truth; excuſeth me from ſhewing how little it hath; I onely ſay, that thoſe who have ſpent ſome time in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> know all reported on this ſubject to be a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57309:23"/>meer fable; never any Prince of this Empire had that Title, neither is the word known in the whole extent of thoſe Dominions.</p>
               <p>That ſome Probability ſpread this report through the world. That this Emperour was the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Presbyter John</hi> of the <hi>Indies;</hi> is undeniable: Firſt, his Kingdom being in the Eaſtern parts, thence, without Examination, if his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire were properly in the <hi>Indies</hi> (onely lying betwixt the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Indus</hi> and <hi>Ganges</hi>) the opinion firſt ſettled on this Baſſis. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The ancient <hi>Presbyter John</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing himſelf a Chriſtian, having for the Embleme of his faith a Croſſe in a hand, and when he went forth or a Journey, a Croſſe carried before him, being beſide a Prieſt, (all which or the greateſt part ſuites with the <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, for that he was by ancient cuſtome a Prieſt, is reported of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57309:24"/>him by tradition and their own Annals; for the Croſſe in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, he often carrieth it in his hand, and all there have it in peculiar reverence and devotion) gave ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently this Errour a ſecond riſe. Thirdly, Ignorant, in what part of <hi>India</hi> his Empire was, having often heard of the Chriſtianity of this King and his Subjects, and without any records of the ancient <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter John,</hi> uninquiſitive men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded him the <hi>Abyſſine</hi> Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: Thus miſtakes are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilded over with the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of truth. We who lived in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> reflecting on this, and often diſcourſing by way of Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, what might moſt probably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get this opinion, derived it from what I ſhall here offer; If a thing ſo obſolete admits any conviction, or what is maintained by common opinion is to be refuted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ethiopia</hi> hath an ancient and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57309:24"/>Cuſtome for ſlaves to petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Maſters and ſubjects their Soveraigne, either in their Ear with an humble and ſubmiſſive voyce, or at a diſtance from ſome eminent place, to tell their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and demand juſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Oppreſſors, ſo placing themſelves, as to be moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently heard, every one crys as loud as his voyce can reach, in the language of his own Province or Nation. The <hi>Portugueſe</hi> (frequent here) cry <hi>Senhor, Senhor, Senhor;</hi> not deſiſting till their buſineſſe be diſpatcht. The Moor crys <hi>Acid, Acid, Acid,</hi> which ſignifies the ſame. The Boor of the Kingdom of <hi>Tigere</hi> ſayes <hi>Adaric, Adaric, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daric.</hi> The Courtier, and thoſe more civilized <hi>Abeto, Abeto, Abe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> intimating the ſame. Others bark like Dogs, howle like Wolves, and by imitating the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent cryes of other Beaſts, are
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57309:25"/>ſo underſtood and known of what place and Province they are.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of an higher Province, in the heart of this great Empire, (where many ages theſe Princes kept their Court) when according to this ancient and uſual Cuſtom, they preſent their Petitions, cry <hi>Jan Coy (i.e.)</hi> my King: (<hi>Jan</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying King, and <hi>Coy</hi> my) which ſuppoſed, for the cleerer proof of what I endeavour to evince, you are to be reminded: That the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bysſines</hi> affirme their Emperours were Prieſts, in teſtimony of that, relate ſome Miracles wrought by them That the <hi>Abysſines</hi> are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Wanderers, particularly undertake pilgrimages to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Land, which being not far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, doth more eaſily engage them in the journey. This they practiſe at preſent, though for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they did it more frequently.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57309:25"/>
               <p>It is alſo notorious, that the <hi>French,</hi> moſt of any Nation of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> uſed the <hi>Levantine</hi> trade, their concourſe was ſo great, that thoſe Infidels ſcarce knew any other Europeans, and called all white men (as they ſtill do) <hi>Franks</hi> by a ſmall corruption from the word <hi>Francois.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> neceſſarily met many <hi>Abysſines</hi> particularly in <hi>Paleſtine</hi> with whom their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was probable about their Nation and Country: The <hi>Abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines</hi> ſpeaking of their King, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly gave him the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, moſt uſual and moſt reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctfull title of <hi>Jan;</hi> neither is it leſs probable, that for the greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of the Royal perſon, they told them their King was a Prieſt; thence was he concluded <hi>Jan</hi> by title, and by office a Prieſt: All know that among us, <hi>Sacerdote</hi> and <hi>Presbytero</hi> are the ſame, which the Latines call <hi>Presbyter</hi> and the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57309:26"/>
                  <hi>French Preſter;</hi> this word joyned to <hi>Jan</hi> begets <hi>Preſter Jan,</hi> which with ſmall addition is corrupted into <hi>Preſter John,</hi> intending the ſame. The <hi>French</hi> returning home were likely to relate what they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved and heard in forraigne parts, ſo ſpred the report, that the King of the <hi>Abysſines</hi> was King and Prieſt <hi>Preſter Jan;</hi> there not being then any knowledge of the true <hi>Preſter John</hi> of the <hi>Indies.</hi> This report, ſet abroad, paſt current, that this famous Prince was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt the Emperour of the <hi>Abysſines,</hi> thence at preſent vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly called <hi>Preſter John</hi> of the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I may without arrogance think the Conjectures and Probabilities on which this Diſcourſe is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, above contempt; both from my own obſervations and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and from the approbation of able Judgments; particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57309:26"/>of great Travellers, and thoſe converſant in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> who found them agree with their informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if any are disſatisfied with this Tract, let them not condemn the good will that offers it, and take my word to acquieſce in any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter propoſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſhort Tract of the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and of the Cauſe of this name by which 'tis commonly known.</head>
               <p>THe Red Sea bounds the Territories of the <hi>Abysſine</hi> Empire which Eaſtward drinks thoſe Waters; having therefore diſcourſed what names the <hi>Abyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine</hi> Emperour <hi>Preſter John,</hi> we may conveniently inquire after the true cauſe that calls that boundary of this Empire the Red Sea.</p>
               <p>The Name of Red Sea com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57309:27"/>given to the <hi>Arabian</hi> Gulf, is very ancient, the miſtake lyes onely in the Reaſon, I ſhall relate what I think moſt ſutable to my own ſurvey and experience.</p>
               <p>The Ancients named the moſt Eaſterly poynt of all <hi>Africa Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum Prom.</hi> the Cape of ſpices; becauſe all thoſe Ships, which brought them from the Coaſt of <hi>India,</hi> and traded with the Ports of that Sea, firſt made that Headland, called at preſent by all Mariners <hi>Guarda fuy,</hi> the Inland is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Adel,</hi> the Inhabitants all Moors and ſtout Souldiers; The defect of Rain, is here the ſame as in <hi>Egypt</hi> ſupplyed by the many and great Rivers, running from the mountains of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> which on that ſide bound this Kingdom. This Promontory is anſwered by another in <hi>Arabia</hi> the happy, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly oppoſite, called <hi>Cape Fartach</hi> from a City and people of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57309:27"/>ſame name inhabiting the main Land, Warlike Moors, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted; the diſtance between theſe two Capes is fifty leagues.</p>
               <p>The largneſſe of the Ocean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be reſtrained from theſe two Promontories to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Red Sea, in length an hundred and fifty leagues: the two ſhoars all the way comming cloſer till they meet at four leagues diſtance in the narroweſt part of the ſtreight where this Sea looſeth the name of the <hi>Arabian Gulf,</hi> and within is called the Red Sea; which extends three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and eighty leagues to <hi>Sues</hi> near the bottom of that ſtreight, in the largeſt place, betwixt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuba</hi> and the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Camaran,</hi> the bredth is forty leagues, near <hi>Sues</hi> onely three, which is yet narrower at the bottom.</p>
               <p>Authors divide this Sea into three parts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Midle is clear
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57309:28"/>and navigable, not without ſome ſmall <hi>Iſlands</hi> and Rocks which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing above water are of little danger; the other two parts near the two ſhoars of <hi>Arabia</hi> and <hi>Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia</hi> are of very bad paſſage, full of Shoals, Rocks and white Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, which, in the night eſpecially, endanger Paſſengers.</p>
               <p>The Mouth is double, made by an <hi>Iſland</hi> called <hi>Nahum</hi> or <hi>Babel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandel,</hi> two leagues in length, leſs than a quarter in breadth, all an high wild barren Rock, parched with the Wind and Sun, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Graſſe, poſſeſt by an abundance of Sea-foul.</p>
               <p>The entrance on the ſide of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia</hi> being clear and deep is the ordinary paſſage for Ships of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; the other part of the mouth toward <hi>Ethiopia</hi> though three leagues over, is ſo full of Shoals, as none venters through, but in little veſſels, called by the Natives <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luas.</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:57309:28"/>Near the <hi>Iſland</hi> is a narrow Channel of a good depth, which I twiſe paſſed, but too dangerous for great Ships, joyning on the <hi>Iſland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Within this ſtraight begins the Red ſea, the Eaſterly Shoar called <hi>Arabia Petrea.</hi> Twelve leagues higher than the mouth is the City <hi>Mocha,</hi> rich and of great trade: Forty further is the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maran;</hi> then follow <hi>Rido, Loia, Zebita</hi> and <hi>Goro;</hi> this latter, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſight, and within half a dayes journey of Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> Hither lyes <hi>Gida</hi> the Port of famous <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha</hi> or <hi>Medina,</hi> where is the tomb of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> At the bottom of this ſtraight is <hi>Sues,</hi> anciently a City of <hi>Heroes;</hi> at preſent a poor fiſhing Village, wanting the trade of Spices from <hi>India</hi> which arrive there as to the Mart of the Eaſt and Levant, and the general Fair of the <hi>Indies.</hi> This City from
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57309:29"/>
                  <hi>Grand Cairo</hi> twenty five leagues; ſixteen from the neareſt part of the <hi>Nile,</hi> and forty one from the Mediterranean.</p>
               <p>Croſſing from hence to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhoar of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> the firſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is <hi>Alcocere,</hi> formerly rich and populous, now a poor Village. Little further, is <hi>Corondelo,</hi> where the Children of <hi>Izrael</hi> at their comming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> paſt over to the other ſhore of <hi>Arabia,</hi> the Sea opening for three leagues, (the diſtance betwixt both the Shoars) into a fair large way, as ſeems to be intimated in the book of<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 19. verſ. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> or dividing it ſelf into twelve parts, as may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſalm. 135. verſ. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi> Not far diſtant, is a place called <hi>Riſa,</hi> whence are exported and import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Commodities from and for <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi> This place is ſituated in the hollow of high mountains, which run along in a Bridge, diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57309:29"/>from moſt parts of the Red Sea;<note n="*" place="margin">The ſame affirmed by <hi>Grotius,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Origine Nili,</hi> of this Shoar of the Red Sea, and of other Mountains in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa. Cap. 12.</hi>
                  </note> when, from theſe mountains to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Sea it is win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, on the other ſide of them is ſummer; ſo <hi>vice verſa.</hi> Hence to <hi>Suaguem,</hi> is deſart, but the Road for <hi>Grand Cairo.</hi> The <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Suaguem,</hi> (where the <hi>Turks</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd me ſometimes Priſoner) is round and little, full of Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants: the reſidence and Court of a <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> having in it the Cuſtom-houſe, where all Merchants Ships unlade. Half the profit, by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, accrews to a King of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, called <hi>Balen.</hi> An hundred leagues further is the <hi>Iſland Maſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> in circuit twelve hundred fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoms, ſhaped like a mans foot. Between this and the main Land, Ships have a convenient Road. Here reſides the <hi>Baſhaw's</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant call'd <hi>Caqua,</hi> judge of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57309:30"/>Cuſtom-houſe. Two leagues fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a Fortreſſe called <hi>Arquico,</hi> (where I was ſometime Priſoner) ill fortified with ſtone and Clay; worſe provided with Amunition, onely defends the water which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day goes in Boats, (called <hi>Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luas</hi>) for <hi>Maſſuba,</hi> deſtitute of any other liquor. Below this <hi>Iſland</hi> is that of <hi>Daleca,</hi> where Pearle is fiſh't; in length ſixteen leagues, ſtraight and populous. Few leagues lower is the Port of <hi>Bailur</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Dancali,</hi> where I landed going into <hi>Ethiopia.</hi> Twelve leagues further, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again to the ſtraight of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belmandel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This general knowledg preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, we come to ſpeak of the Original of the name, for which divers reaſons are given. By my Obſervations, in ſix weeks I was at one time upon that Sea, and twenty dayes at another, when my
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57309:30"/>Inquiries were very ſevere and ſcrupulous, I found not any opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion warrantably grounded. So general a Name is vainly contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and not to be allowed, by certain red ſpots which appear, and to ſome, ſeem to proceed, from certain parts of a Whale; thoſe ſpots not alwayes appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Whales being very few in thoſe ſhallows; in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, out of the ſtraight there are many. Neither did I in all my voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age upon that Sea obſerve any ſuch diſcolouring.</p>
               <p>A ſecond Reaſon for this Name is fetch'd from ſome Hills of red earth, whoſe duſt carried by the fury of the Winds and falling into the waters, changeth it to this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: This opinion ſeems fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, for by curious ſearch, no ſuch Hills are diſcoverable, neither could the Duſt be ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to make the ſpots ſo great, as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57309:31"/>would give the General name to the whole Sea. Others contend, that the red Coral which grows in the bottom of this Sea, by reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the water begets the ſame apparent colour, and gives the name: This Opinion is equally falſe: The Coral at the bottom of the Sea being not red enough to create any ſuch apparent colour or name; the red is faint, nearer white, than any other colour, enli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened by an Artificial compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Upon the ſhore of this Sea I have gatheted ſome, not in bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches but in little pieces, called ſhop-ware, (being ground and there expoſed) The Sun gave it out of the water a very vivid co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; this confirm'd me, that the name proceeded from the Coral.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now declare my opinion, if any voyce be permitted me up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Subject. What I ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, I ſaw with my Eyes, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57309:31"/>diſcours'd the matter with my Companions capable of giving their Judgment. Being Priſoner to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and ſayling in thoſe Seas, one of my companions and of the Company of Jeſus hapen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Patriarch of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently skill'd in Divine and Prophane Learning; We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the water of that Sea, not different from that of the Ocean; in ſome places we obſerved, a long tract of water bluiſh, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the great depth: In others, found divers white ſpots proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the white ſand, and the ſhallowneſſe: Other places were diſcoloured green, by the mudd which covered the bottom. In o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the water, where it was as clear as in any other Sea, were ſome reddiſh ſpots; We found theſe ſpots (which were many) to be cauſed by a weed reſembling that we cal <hi>Cargaco,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:57309:32"/>rooted in the bottom; ſome that was looſe and ſwum almoſt on the ſurface of the water we took up, and caſting Anchor thereabouts, made an Indian dive to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom for more. Upon ſtrict ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, it prov'd to be that the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> call <hi>Sufo,</hi> which in great quantity, grows in <hi>India</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers parts of <hi>Aſia.</hi> The ſame name of <hi>Sufo,</hi> is given to the ſeed; to a meat made of it, like Almond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milk, well taſted, (and often eaten by me) and to the Flower, which reſembles <hi>Saffron</hi> and may be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken for it. Of this is made a Red-colour call'd <hi>Sufo,</hi> uſed for dying cloath in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> and <hi>India</hi> (ſome of which Cloath furniſh'd my poor Church in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> with a ſure of Hangings) The weed, ſeed, meat, flower, and colour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the ſame name of <hi>Sufo,</hi> which conſidered, put us in mind, that the Scripture, in St. <hi>Jerome's</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:57309:32"/>Tranſlation calls the Red Sea, in ſtead of <hi>Mare Rubrum, Bahar Suf,</hi> making <hi>Suf</hi> and Red the ſame in <hi>Hebrew:</hi> This Sea therefore, being ſo near rather between <hi>Ethiopia</hi> and <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> and in both places <hi>Suf</hi> ſignifying Red, our obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on named the Sea, not from any ſuch colour appearing in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but from the growth of that weed, which in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thìopian</hi> language ſignifies <hi>Rubrum.</hi> And by Experiment, the flower boyled, and mixt with juyce of limes, makes ſo beautifull a Red, that it's nearer an incarnate than Red, and if durable would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly of great eſteem.</p>
               <p>Conſidering the weakneſſe of the other reaſons; from our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe had on that Sea, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the name derived from no other cauſe, than from the growth of the weed <hi>Sufo;</hi> inſufficient of it ſelf to produce that colour, but
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:57309:33"/>whoſe flower makes it, and the Natives give the name of the weed to the Colour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Diſcourſe of <hi>Palme-trees,</hi> Of their Variety, their Fruit, (and the uſefullneſse of it,) Of their proper Soyle.</head>
               <p>OF all the Trees, created by God Almighty for the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Earth and ſervice of Man, the <hi>Palme-tree</hi> is the moſt uſefull and profitable to humane ſociety: Though for this end the Author of Nature created all Plants, all which, with all their vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue are at man's devotion, yet none ſerves ſo munificently, and for ſo many uſes as the <hi>Palm-tree.</hi> For from her deepeſt roots, which take firſt poſſeſſion of the Earth and vegetation, to the higheſt leaf of her adorned head, with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:57309:33"/>propriety, excellency of her fruit, in fine, with all her virtue, is man ſubſtantially ſerved, and paid his due tribute; What I ſhall ſay in this Tract will diſengage this truth.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Palme-tree</hi> is advanced by one peculiar Excellency, by which, without any ſecond, ſhe hath the advantage of all other Trees, well ſatisfied in paying man once a year their Tribute, reſt from their labour. The <hi>Palme-tree</hi> takes no repoſe, but every month in the year preſents new fruit: A beautifull cluſter of thirty, forty, ſometimes more Cocoes, or nuts monthly appearing; and though not above ſeven, twelve at the moſt, come to be ripe and attain the laſt perfection, (there not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrength and nouriſhment for ſo many) yet is it queſtionleſs, that the <hi>Palme-tree</hi> by her fruitfulneſſe was by God peculiarly created
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57309:34"/>for the advantage of mankind; If Vigour to perform her natural propenſity be wanting, yet is her generous inclination apparent.</p>
               <p>We may truly ſay of the <hi>Palme-tree,</hi> that not being, (which is not contended for) that ſo ſingular and excellent tree, peculiar to the happineſſe of Heaven, which the<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 22. verſ. 2.</note> Scripture calls the Tree of life, which beareth twelve manner of fruits, and yieldeth her fruit every month, yet that it is a ſimilitude or Embleme of that faecundity. That by the frequency and goodneſſe of her fruit, and by the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit man enjoys by it, it is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Tree of life on Earth, as the other is truly in Heaven, and the moſt beneficial the earth produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, ſhall appear in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>The moſt favourable Climate or Soyle, and which with greateſt propriety and in moſt abundance
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57309:34"/>produceth this famous Tree, (which ſtrangers, divine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane writings, and the Natives, in the property of their language call'd the <hi>Palm-tree</hi>) is <hi>Aſia,</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly that part of it, called <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> containing the Kingdoms and Provinces, which lye betwixt, and are bounded by the two famous Rivers <hi>Indus</hi> and <hi>Ganges,</hi> both ſo well known in Hiſtory. How re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious fables have made <hi>Ganges,</hi> and how vain a ſanctity, blind I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry attributed to thoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, (in which to waſh, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to be cleanſed from fault and puniſhment, and be ſecured of Salvation) much might be ſaid, by what I have obſerved and heard of this ſuperſtition; but that is not the task of this diſcourſe, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely of <hi>Palme-trees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The land neareſt the Sea ſide produceth the faireſt; the Air from the Sea, being very favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:57309:35"/>and benigne to them. Though ſtrangers give the ſame name of <hi>Palm-tree</hi> to divers ſorts of this tree, all cannot challenge it, neither enjoy the Excellencies, proper to the <hi>Palme-tree</hi> called <hi>Coco:</hi> The Natives diſtinguiſh them by particular names, and reckon up eight ſorts, all different in their Truncks, leaves, fruit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and appearance, yet enjoy the general name of <hi>Palme-trees,</hi> having I know not what likeneſſe, by which they lay claime to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the proper name of each ſpecies.</p>
               <p>The chiefeſt and moſt famous, and which beſt retains the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Palme-tree,</hi> is that which bears <hi>Coco's;</hi> of theſe ſome are wilde, ſome cultivated, ſome, but few, called <hi>Barcas,</hi> which amongſt them ſignifie excellent; and when they knaviſhly put off any thing for excellent, they ſay 'tis <hi>Barca.</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:57309:35"/>The Nut <hi>Barca</hi> is ſavoury, whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, not to be ſurfeited on, though eaten in never ſo great a quantity; But as all Trees are not <hi>Barca's,</hi> ſo not all the Nuts, and the ſame Tree bears <hi>Barca's</hi> and others: The Natives diſtinguiſh and very much vallue them. The Nut <hi>Barca,</hi> when crude and unripe is called <hi>Lanha Taugi (i.e.)</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſweet; is refreſhing, wholeſome, of great uſe in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. If the Roots of this Tree touch the Sea or any brackiſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the bearing is very much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
               <p>Of the other ſeven ſorts, ſome are eſteemed wild, from their fruit, ſoyle, and the little manuring they require. The Tree called <hi>Cajuri,</hi> is the peculiar one which bears <hi>Dates,</hi> though in <hi>India</hi> this tree yields none, but affords a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain liquor which they diſtil, and of it make wine. Another ſort
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:57309:36"/>named <hi>Trefulim,</hi> from her fruit of the ſame name <hi>Arequeira</hi> of whoſe leaves are made great umbrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, large enough to ſhelter one or two men from the rigour of the Sun or rain, without which none could travell: There are leſſe, for the ſame uſe, like our umbrellas, which alſo keep off the raine. This tree yields no fruit.</p>
               <p>Another tree there is, (the name not much in uſe,) by the leafe, trunck, and make, of the race of <hi>Palme-trees;</hi> the fruit called <hi>de Rapoſa (i.e.)</hi> the <hi>Foxes</hi> fruit; eaten, of no good taſte, ſuch a Crab as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ripens, and if brought to matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, would prove a wild <hi>Date,</hi> being ſo in the form, colour, bunch or cluſter. The tree called <hi>Berlim,</hi> bears no fruit, onely uſed for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning Churches; the boughs of ſo fit a ſize and proportion for this uſe, as if foly created by God
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57309:36"/>almighty for his ſervice, not of leſs eſteem and value, becauſe ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to divine worſhip, this dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſupplyes the defect of fruit for the ſervice of man, and may reaſonably rank the tree above the fruitfull.</p>
               <p>The laſt the Earth produceth, called <hi>Macomeira,</hi> is without doubt a ſpecies of the <hi>Palme-tree;</hi> her fruit in cluſters of thirty or more, every one as big as an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Apple; when ripe, of a Date-colour, and very gratefull, the rind as hard as Tow, oftner ſuck'd than eaten; if ſwallowed, of very hard diſgeſtion; In ſent, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the<note n="*" place="margin">Esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the best Apple in <hi>Portugal.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Camoeſa:</hi> the ſtone, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Coquinho,</hi> very hard, though green, is ſoveraign againſt many diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>Palme-trees</hi> the Earth produceth, which challeng a right in that name. The Sea affords one, which though at the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57309:37"/>bottom of the deep and ſo undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, the fruit called <hi>Coco,</hi> and ſurnamed <hi>Maldiva,</hi> (becauſe the Sea about thoſe <hi>Iſlands</hi> affords that Plant in greateſt abundance) gives us the Information. The <hi>Maldives</hi> are a Ridge of great and ſmall <hi>Iſlands,</hi> reaching near two hundred leagues, are counted from North to South, diſtant from the ſhoar, thirty or forty leagues, the Natives affirme them to be Eleven thouſand: He was at leiſure, and of no ſmall curioſity who counted them. But not to enquire too ſtrictly and minutely into their number, the Ocean a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe <hi>Iſlands</hi> moſt abound with theſe Nuts, which are rare; the Sea caſts them upon the ſhoar, or they ſwim upon the water, yet have I ſeen them from the coaſt of <hi>Melinde</hi> to the Cape of <hi>Guarda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuy,</hi> for above two hundred leagues: they are little leſs than a
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57309:37"/>man's head, grow two together, joyned one to the other, not all along, but near two thirds; the colour of the Rind, (which is hard though thin) black; the Europe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans make of it Bodies of Birds, <hi>e. g.</hi> of a Peacock, adding to it feet, neck, head and wings, and that perfection of parts the Bird de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned requires. The Pulpe or kernell of this fruit is very firme, as in thoſe that grow at Land; of very great eſteem with the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; I have ſeen it ſold for its weight in ſilver, being eſteemed a ſingular Remedy againſt all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, particularly againſt poyſon, pounded in a Mortar (made for that purpoſe) with a little water, till it grows white, and ſo drank. In <hi>India</hi> they make frequent uſe of this remedy, having it in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. So much of the <hi>Palme-tree</hi> and the Nutt <hi>Maldiva;</hi> I am now to diſcourſe of the ineſtimable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57309:38"/>of the other ſorts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Palme-trees,</hi> of what ſpecies ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, have neither a thick Trunck, nor boughes like other trees. As they grow in height, their boughes come out at the top, and open to make room for others; as the old ones fall, they leave an impreſſion in the Tree where they were; If any have two truncks, the thing is very peculiar, and ſhewn as noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: I have ſeen one or two ſuch, in all the time and places I was in <hi>India:</hi> One of them near the Coaſt of <hi>Melinde,</hi> whence I imbarked for the <hi>Iſland Pate,</hi> to ſee a thing ſo remarkable. The tree called <hi>Macomeira,</hi> (from the fruit named <hi>Macoma</hi>) is the onely one, that grown to the height of a man, divides her ſelf into two trunks, each of which at the ſame diſtance is divided into other two, ſo grows on, each Trunck producing two, till ſhe arrives to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57309:38"/>that hight, the Natives allow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the ſpecies. The tree called <hi>Trafulim</hi> grows the tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt, and for hight, were the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe proportionable, (celfity is more conſiderable in this, than any other of the ſorts) and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the wood ſolid, and ſtrong, might make a Maſt for a great Veſſel, but it wants ſufficient ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, neither are thoſe trees which yield <hi>Coco's</hi> proper for that uſe; In little Veſſels they ſerve, as will be immediately related.</p>
               <p>That the moſt favourable ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation for the growth and fertility of theſe trees is the ground near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the Sea, has been ſaid before: and if the roots reach the mudd of ſalt-water, they thrive beſt with that watering. Experience hath found, that thoſe <hi>Palme-trees,</hi> which grow neareſt houſes inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, are the moſt fruitfull; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Natives, if poſſible, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:57309:39"/>to dwell in the <hi>Palme-Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards,</hi> having there their goods and Eſtates, (as will preſently be ſaid) their pleaſure and recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Theſe are the reall Eſtates in <hi>India,</hi> as Vineyards and Olive-yards in <hi>Europe:</hi> amongſt theſe is arable Land, which they ſow, and have a Crop of Rice, Wheat and other grain; I have ſeen fair and beautifull <hi>Palme-trees</hi> in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, remote from the Sea, always in Plains, never upon Hills, where they come to no maturity, either becauſe in low grounds they ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one the other, or that on the hills the wind ſhakes them too violently, to the no little detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their fruit, being tall and tender with all their boughes and fruit on the top, they are obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the wind, the whole weight being at the head, the body high, tender and fragile: they may be fitly compar'd to the Maſt of a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57309:39"/>ſhip with round top and top-maſt without the help of ſhrouds to ſupport it.</p>
               <p>Theſe trees are planted, by ſowing the <hi>Coco's</hi> or Nuts in a Bed, and covering them with Earth: A little time will put forth a ſhoot, the ordinary product of ſeed; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at ſome growth, they are tranſplanted into a place deſigned for that purpoſe. There ranked in fit diſtance, order and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where they remain till arrive to perfection, And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing planted in a line, make a fair ſhew in the field, ſo pleaſant to the Natives, that no Garden in <hi>Europe</hi> is with more care manured, or of greater, if of equal ſatisfact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. This hath been experienced by preſenting them with our Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, who neglect them and ſigh after the <hi>Palme-trees</hi> of their own Country; though there is not a more melancholy and unpleaſant
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:57309:40"/>ſight to the Europeans, than to be in a Palme-Orchard, where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be ſeen but Truncks of Trees ſet in order, which appear withered without any foliage; all the greeneſſe being above, the ſight there is little enjoyed; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held at a diſtance, no Proſpect ſo gratefull. Being young plants, their mortall Enemies are the Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, which riſle their beauty, and with their teeth do them no little damage; that begets a neceſſity to encompaſſe them with fences.</p>
               <p>Theſe Plants are manured with ſmall expence, ordinarily they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not much watering: grown to ſome bigneſſe, they lay Aſhes to their Roots, all ſorts of ſhell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, particularly, little fiſh, called by the Natives <hi>Cuta,</hi> putrefied at the foot of the tree, are of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable effect; but all trees cannot be ſo indulged; this is ſupplyed by Mud taken out of ſalt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57309:40"/>by which their fruitfulneſſe is very much advanced. They bear fruit at five years if planted in ſoft Artificial Beds, ſo taking root ſooner and with greater eaſe; At ſeven, if the Earth be firme and hard, ſpreading their roots leiſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with more difficulty. I one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know one ſpot of Ground in the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Ceilaon</hi> ſo fruitfull and proper for theſe trees, that in two years they come to their growth, get ſtrength, and are laden with fruit.</p>
               <p>The fruit of this tree, (whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſpecies is) comes forth thus; From the ſtem of the <hi>Palme,</hi> ſhoots out a Twig, made like a mans Arme, not unlike a Mooriſh ſimiter, which the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves call <hi>Poyo.</hi> This opens and puts forth a cluſter of thirty, fifty, eighty, ſometimes an hundred <hi>Coquinhos</hi> or Nuts, about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an Haſle-nut; ſhould all
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57309:41"/>come to perfection the quantity were ſtupendious, but the Parent wanting ſap and nouriſhment for ſo many young ones, the greateſt part falls off and comes to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; few remain of the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing multitude, twelve or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen in every cluſter may come to maturity, according to the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ground, or the ſoyling implyed: Nature ſupplies the loſt ones, by putting forth imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately another cluſter before the firſt is ripe or cleared of the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; the ſame happens to the latter fruit, and ſo to more, every month a bunch appearing, and all the trees having four or five cluſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of different ages, ſome in the bloſſom, others newly cleared of the flower, as big as ordinary nuts, others larger, ſome come to perfection: The <hi>Palme-tree</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles an indulgent mother, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viron'd with greater and ſmaller
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:57309:41"/>Children, at the ſame time feeding theſe and bearing others; a rarity not experienced in other trees.</p>
               <p>The Emolument of this fruit <hi>Coco</hi> is very extraordinary, for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers wayes it proves good meat; while the kernell is yet in water and full of liquor, the Nut green, and not come to maturity, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives drink it as an exquiſite Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallo, being ſweet and recreative, affording a good Cup of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome water called <hi>Lanha;</hi> arrived to a greater conſiſtence, like that of Cream, they eat it with ſpoons, then called <hi>Cocanha:</hi> come to the laſt perfection, it is eaten, is ſavory and well taſted: but being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly hot and of hard digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, much of it is unwholeſome, the Nut <hi>Barca</hi> excepted, which is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury and harmleſſe. The thin Rind which covers the kernell, black, and good in Medicine.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:57309:42"/>This Nut grated and put into the hollow joynts of Canes called <hi>Bambus</hi> is boyled, and of it made<note n="*" place="margin">A Meat like the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micelli, and near' the Conſistence of our Grout.</note> 
                  <hi>Cuſcus.</hi> The gratings, ſteeped in water and ſqueezed, the milk they yield, makes a kind of broath, frequent amongſt them called <hi>Cerul,</hi> which is very delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: the Nut <hi>Coco</hi> is eaten other different wayes, which deſervedly advance the eſteem of this provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The two Rinds taken off, the kernell divided into two parts, and expoſed to dry in the Sun, when dryed is called <hi>Copra,</hi> of this, great quantities, go for the Inland Country, and where no Olive-trees grow, Oyle made of it, which is toothſom, wholeſom, good for wounds and ſores. This <hi>Copra</hi> eaten with <hi>Igra,</hi> (a ſort of courſe muſcovados ſugar) made of the ſweat of the <hi>Palme tree,</hi> as ſhall immediately be related) is a great dainty with the <hi>Indians.</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:57309:42"/>And that no part of the <hi>Coco</hi> may ſeem not valuable, and declaring the obligation humane life hath to the Palmtree, The outmoſt Rind, called <hi>Cairo,</hi> not unlike Tow, well macerated and drawn into threds, affords all ſorts of fine Thred, and Ropes big enough for the greateſt Veſſels and Ships, which are of great eſteem for good and ſecure Cables, they will endure ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and rot not in Salt-water; theſe advantages have they above Cables made of Hemp. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Rind, the immediate cover of the <hi>Coco,</hi> when green, is eaten like <hi>Chardons,</hi> is tender, crackles in the mouth, and of the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the ſtomach, blacks the lips and fingers like <hi>Chardons;</hi> when ripe is very hard and thin, called <hi>Charetta,</hi> made up for divers uſes; Chark'd, it admirably tempers I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, accordingly eſteemed by Artificers.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:57309:43"/>
               <p>Beſides the related, divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Emoluments accrue from the Palmtree and her Fruit; the Palm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree alone being ſufficient to build, rig, and fraight a ſhip, with bread, Wine, water, Oyle, Vinegar, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and other Commodities, all afforded by the Palmtree. I have ſayled in Veſſels, where the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom and the whole <hi>Cargo</hi> hath been from the munificence of the Palmtree; I will take upon me to make good what I have aſſerted.</p>
               <p>The Veſſels are by the Natives called <hi>Pangayos,</hi> on which I have Coaſted the land of <hi>Melinde,</hi> and gone into the <hi>Red-Sea:</hi> they ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not far from ſhoar, being weak, without any binding of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, unable to endure any ſtreſs of weather, or beating of the waves, therefore lanch not out into the main Ocean. The Palmtree yields Plank, though weak and ſpungy, as if made of Tow: the Planks are
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57309:43"/>ſowed together with fine thred made of the outmoſt Rind of the Nut (as hath been ſaid) the ſeams are Caulk'd with Okum of <hi>Cairo,</hi> after paid over (as is uſual) with the fat of Fiſh, ſerving inſtead of hot Pitch: where there is any uſe of Nails, that is ſupplyed by woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Pins, made of a certain ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Palmtree; the Maſt is provided by the ſame Tree, and requires not much pains to faſhion it; Ropes of all bigneſſes are made of <hi>Cayro (i.e)</hi> the rind of the <hi>Coco:</hi> Sayls are woven of the Leavs of the Palmtree called <hi>Cajuris,</hi> of which are alſo made Sacks (called <hi>Macondas</hi>) in which they carry Millet, or any other thing at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; Bread (before mentioned) the ſame Nut ſupplies, either dry, then called <hi>Copra,</hi> or green, when named <hi>Puto;</hi> which grated and put into hollow Canes is <hi>Cuſcus:</hi> Water proceeds from the ſame
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:57309:44"/>Nuts being green, before the Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel arrives to a due conſiſtency, clear as Rock water, freſher and better: Oyle is made of <hi>Copra</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> the Nut dryed in the Sun) in great quantity uſed by all people in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> having no other of their own growth, beſides what is drawn from a ſeed called <hi>Gergelim,</hi> of ſmall value, onely uſed by the poor.</p>
               <p>The Wine requires more pains and aſſiduity: When the <hi>Palm-tree</hi> puts forth her ſhoot or <hi>Poyo</hi> (ſhap'd like a <hi>Mooriſh Simiter</hi>) before the cluſter appears, they cut three fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers breadth from the point, and tying it near the Inciſion with a reed to prevent ſlitting, put the end of the ſhoot into a pitcher made for that purpoſe, called <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go;</hi> leaving it there, the ſhoots, like Vines pruned, but in greater abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, weep that juyce, which ſhould have produced <hi>Coco's.</hi> This Liquor is twice drawn in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57309:44"/>day; in the morning, that which was wept by night, and in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, the diſtillation of the day: At theſe times, a man deputed to that buſineſs, and of a certain Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, called <hi>Bandarins,</hi> with a goad hung at his girdle, and with a Pruning-hook in his hand, climbs the talleſt Palmtree: ſome of which, peculiarly thoſe called <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juris,</hi> are of a prodigious height, they climb as on a Ladder by notches made in the Trunck of the Tree, and with as much ſecurity as Sea-men run up to the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top: In other leſs Palmtrees, (ſeeming to be of that Race which yields <hi>Dates</hi>) they make a hole in the Trunck, there lodging a Cane through which the Liquor diſtills, which when the Tree affords, ſhe bears no <hi>Coco's.</hi> This Liquor is ſweet, medicinal, clears the Body from humours, is drunk for a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallo,</hi> and called <hi>Sura;</hi> ſet to the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57309:45"/>Fire in great Veſſels, is diſtilled as in a Limbeck, with this caution, That they continually caſt cold water upon the Veſſel, leaſt as ſtrong water, it ſhould take fire, This is the Wine made of the Palm-tree, called by the Natives <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rraca,</hi> it entoxicates in litle quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, flyes to the head, and is of ſtrange effect; much more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full if diſtilled over again, when it becomes a <hi>Quinteſſence.</hi> Of this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rraca</hi> is made excellent Vinegar, by putting into it two or three fired ſticks, or a great ſtone well heated. Sugar is made of the ſweet <hi>Sura</hi> coming freſh from the Tree, which boyled till it coagulates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes good Sugar, perfect in taſt and colour. The Merchandize af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded by the Palmtree, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den on Veſſels, are dryed <hi>Coco's</hi> or Nuts, the Rind, and many other Commodities before mentioned: this juſtifies the Palm-tree's build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57309:45"/>rigging and lading a Veſſel with goods and Ship-proviſions for the Mariners; all her own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</p>
               <p>The Palmtree being ſo benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and advantageous to humane life, doubtleſs no Tree in any known part of the World may come into competition with it; and amongſt all her advantages, no other ſo well ſatisfies the ſight when laden with great and ſmaller Cluſters, ſome ripe, others colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſome in the bloſſom, others forwarder; the grateful appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of her Fruit is no leſs pleaſant than her admirable foecundity: Her tallneſs not inferior to a high <hi>Cyprus-tree,</hi> her Trunck ſlender, without the help of Boughs to climb by, her Nuts retired at the top, amongſt her leavs and branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, makes her reſemble a fond Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, bringing her Children about her the better to preſerve them,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:57309:46"/>and cutting off all intercourſe tending to their deſtruction.</p>
               <p>All places produce not <hi>Coco's</hi> of the ſame bigneſs, which are great or ſmall according to the nature of the Climate, and quality of the Soyl fitted for the production of that fruit. The Coaſt of <hi>Malabar</hi> being cool, and abounding with Rivers (which ſpring in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Gate,</hi> to whoſe foot this Coaſt extends) affords ſuch large and fair <hi>Coco's</hi> that the <hi>Lanhas (i. e.)</hi> young and imperfect Nuts of <hi>Cochim</hi> and thoſe Territories, are every one ſufficient to quench the thirſt of two perſons. After theſe are cryed up theſe of the Iſland of <hi>Ceilon,</hi> where the ground is very rank and luxuriant, yet inferiour to the Soyl of <hi>Malaca,</hi> and the places adjoyning, where the <hi>Coco's</hi> are the greateſt. Thoſe of <hi>Arabia the Happy</hi> are fairer than any yet ſpoken of; the goodneſs of the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57309:46"/>Soyl, and nature of the Climate, being proportionably advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the name of <hi>Happy</hi> proves it. Of all theſe places and ſorts of Fruit I am an Eye-witneſs; Two peculiar virtues of theſe <hi>Coco's,</hi> are not to be paſſed over in ſilence: The firſt, That when the Cluſter begins to appear, being yet co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with the flower; gathered, pounded, boyled in three pints of Cows milk, tis an infallible cure for the <hi>Yellow-jaundies;</hi> beſide the opinion had of this remedy, I ſpeak by experience, having with it in few days cured one troubled with this diſeaſe. The ſecond is, That in the opinion of the Women, (where fancy moſt domineers) the water of <hi>Lanhas</hi> makes a waſh for the face, which eminently betters the Complexion, either by creating it where Nature beſtow'd it not, or advancing it where Nature is deficient, or preſerving it where it
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:57309:47"/>was naturally allowed. From what hath been ſaid, is evidently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; That if the Author of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture created all Trees for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of man, the Palmtree of all thoſe doth moſt induſtruouſly ſerve and advantage him, by ſo many wayes, and ſo conſiderable productions; and becauſe that which bears <hi>Dates</hi> is of the true Race of Palmtrees, ſomthing is to be ſaid of that and her Fruit.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Trees which bear <hi>Dates,</hi> yield them not in <hi>India;</hi> there on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affording the <hi>Sura</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, of which Wine is made Northward, thoſe Trees grow in the greateſt quantity; ſome have <hi>Dates,</hi> which appear in fair cluſters but come not to maturity: the reaſon muſt be in the Climate which favours them not. In <hi>Africa</hi> they attain the higheſt perfection, <hi>Dates</hi> being the natural Fruit of that part of the World; thoſe of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57309:47"/>
                  <hi>Arabia,</hi> where they grow in great quantities, are excellent; pleaſant to the ſight in beautiful Cluſters, (which beginning to ripen appear in various colours, conſiſting of a faint Vermilian, and paled white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, called the <hi>Date-colour</hi>) and more acceptable to the taſt. <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> produceth divers ſorts, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <hi>the Happy;</hi> (<hi>Petrea</hi> is not without them.) A baſer ſort there is, which ſerves for common ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance, given to Horſes for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender: Others there are of a more exquiſite taſt and value, amongſt them thoſe called <hi>Muxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> which are the leaſt, but natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally recompenced by an excellent flavour; few of them exported out of <hi>Arabia;</hi> the <hi>Xarifes</hi> reſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them for themſelves as excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and give the reaſon that their exquiſitneſs makes them properly theirs, challenging the beſt things in the World, as the poſterity of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57309:48"/>
                  <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and for the Religion they profeſs, which they would falſly put off for Orthodox. This Fruit ripens not upon the Tree if there be not near it, or in ſight, the Fruit called the <hi>Male;</hi> a ſecret in Nature found by experience, the cauſe yet undiſcovered.</p>
               <p>Writing this, I remember a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I had with an Old man, but a credulous Chriſtian; As we were eating ſome of theſe <hi>Dates,</hi> I was obſerving, That the ſtone beaten and drank in water was good for Women in ſtrong labour, to eaſe their pangs, and facilitate their Delivery; and that it had on one ſide the perfect ſhape of the letter O. the good Old man in great devotion and ſimplicity, anſwered me with a ſtory, which with him paſſed for infallible; <hi>That the letter</hi> O, <hi>remained upon the ſtone of a</hi> Date, <hi>for a remembrance that our</hi> Bleſſed Lady <hi>the Virgin,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:57309:48"/>with her Divine Babe in her arms, reſting her ſelf at the foot of a</hi> Palm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, (<hi>which inclined her Branches, and offered a Cluſter of</hi> Dates <hi>to her Creatour</hi>) <hi>our</hi> Lady <hi>pluck'd ſome of the</hi> Dates, <hi>and eating them, ſatisfied with the taſt and flavour, cryed out in amazement,</hi> Oh how ſweet they are! <hi>this Exclamation engraved the letter</hi> O; <hi>firſt word of her ſpeech upon the</hi> Date-ſtone, <hi>which being very hard, better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it.</hi> I have related this ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of more piety and plain devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than truth and certainty, for the Readers diverſion and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment; Yet not to believe this Old-wives Fable would be with them ſcandalous. There are ſome Palmtrees which bear a Fruit cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Macomas,</hi> of a ſingular virtue, (beſides their ſcent, more grateful than that of a <hi>Camojeſa,</hi> and their perfect <hi>Date colour:</hi>) This Fruit eaten upon an overcharged ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57309:49"/>after too much repletion, in a very little time digeſts all, and begets a freſh Appetite; God be praiſed theſe Trees are ſo far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from Europe, that our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures are without the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their Fruit, which would advance the luxury of thoſe men St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Quorum Venter Deus eſt,</hi> whoſe God is their Belly, from their frequent ſacrifices made to it; I have had experience of this natural virtue of this Fruit: The Stone eaten is good againſt <hi>Hypocondraical</hi> Vapours.</p>
               <p>Another Fruit called <hi>Trefolim</hi> (which hath the name of the Tree which bears it) grows in Cluſters of fifteen or more, each as big as two fiſts joyned; the firſt colour green, when ripe ends in a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple colour; opened, hath three partitions, repleat with a certain ſubſtance like ill coagulated milk; freſh and cooling, of an inſipid
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:57309:49"/>taſt, yet commonly eaten for a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallo;</hi> the Kernell of a faint white; the Fruit of a Palmtree called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reica,</hi> not much differing from the <hi>Trefolim,</hi> is of eminent eſteem with the Native <hi>Indians:</hi> The Iſland of <hi>Ceilon</hi> produceth the moſt and beſt. Theſe <hi>Coco's</hi> are exported and prove good Merchandize, not bigger ordinarily than an Haſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut, the Kernell firm and hard, the uſual dainty of the <hi>Indians,</hi> who accuſtomed to chaw the leaf of an herb bigger, thicker, and of a clearer green than an Ivy-leaf, are forced to champ <hi>Areica;</hi> from warming and recovering the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, eſteemed very cordial and delicious; the juyce contracteth the mouth like Alum, or a <hi>Cypreſs-Apple</hi> if chawed, which ſometimes ſupplyes the virtue of <hi>Areica,</hi> this fruit like <hi>Dates</hi> grows in Cluſters, two hundred or more counted in a bunch; exquiſite Beads are made
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:57309:50"/>of them, white, ſtreak'd with black: The <hi>Indians</hi> ſo dote on this fruit, as to have it common in their mouths, thence tranſmit the juyce to their ſtomach, which it fortifies and ſtrengthens, faſtens the teeth and helps digeſtion; therefore the laſt thing done at meals is to chaw a piece of this, which they as high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prize, as the <hi>Europeans</hi> their choyceſt fruit; but from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of both, I am for my Country-men. The <hi>Coco</hi> or Nut of <hi>Maldiva</hi> is another fruit of the Palmtree; we have already ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of its ſhape, virtue, price, and value; the fruit commonly called <hi>Coco</hi> is found on the Sea, or caſt upon the ſhoar, the make of the Tree which produceth them, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath hid at the bottom of the deep, and charged her ſelf with its Culture. I ſhall conclude this Diſcourſe of Palmtrees, with this obſervation, That nothing has life
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:57309:50"/>without Enemies of that life, which by divers wayes and ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems attempt and aſſault it: The vegetation of the <hi>Palme-tree</hi> wants not theſe, by the <hi>Indians</hi> called ſickneſſes and diſeaſes, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice this ſo adventageous Tree and her fruit, by which Man is ſo plentifully provided, as he is ſaid to live and dye, the ſame is ſaid of the Palmetree, which, like man, hath infirmities and diſeaſes, by which, and many accidents, they pine away, decay, dry up, and at laſt dye. There is a long liſt of diſeaſes incident to this Tree, which work her death if Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are not timely applyed.</p>
               <p>A mortall Enemy to this Tree, is a certain ſpecies of black wormes, which are naturally ſo provided, as eaſily to pierce any Timber green or dry, thereby conveying themſelves into the heart of it, neither doth this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:57309:51"/>much time, they deſiſting not till they arrive at the inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſap, living on what they corrode and deface, caſting out the remainder. This in the <hi>Palme-tree</hi> is effected with more facility and leſs time, the wood being tender, and the marrow (the part fed upon) ſavory: With greater guſto, and by natural inſtinct, they get to the top of the Tree; and what they did in the Trunck, do in the Eye of the <hi>Palme-tree,</hi> with more eaſe and ſatisfaction; devouring the Eye, which is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly white, tender, ſweet, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and gratefull, to a miracle. A <hi>Palme-tree</hi> is often cut down, to come at the Eye, as her choyceſt fruit and dainty; I have had great experience of its goodneſſe; the worme hath no ill palate in the choyce of this morſell; timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy not applyed, the worm leaves not, till, (as they call it) ſhe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57309:51"/>procures the death of the poor Tree. To prevent this, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor, or thoſe called Bandarins, (the onely men charged with theſe Trees) are obliged to watch theſe thieves; and with Iron In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, invented for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, (ſometimes made ſtreight, when the holes go ſo, ſometimes crooked when they make their way by turnings and meanders) to purſue them, till they ſeize them, and upon their forked point draw them out dead.</p>
               <p>Another diſtemper faſtens on theſe Trees, through the careleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or little dexterity of the Bandarins, when they clime the Tree, to empty the Sura, out of the Gorgo or Veſſel, into their Gourds; if by chance, any drop lights on the Tree, by a natural malignity, it engenders another worme which attaques and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours the Eye. This diſaſter is
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57309:52"/>deſperate beyond the help of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, the Maſter looſeth the Tree, but the Cuſtom of the Country, obligeth the Bandarin to make ſatisfaction: the price of every ſuch neglect is ten <hi>Pardaos,</hi> in our money, three<note n="*" place="margin">'twenty five ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</note> 
                  <hi>Mil-Rees:</hi> The great abundance of theſe trees in <hi>India,</hi> leſſens the mulct; Every <hi>Palme-tree</hi> well manured, and growing in good ground, yields the owner one <hi>Pardao</hi> year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. According to this Eſtimate, every Proprietary, gives a near gueſſe at the Rent of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard.</p>
               <p>A third diſeaſe ſeizeth this Tree (her Emolument to man ſeeming to beget her more Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to leſſen her value) which is no open and violent adverſary, but created by the ſame Earth, which gives growth and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the root of the tree, and is no faint reſemblance of a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:57309:52"/>Nurſe, who for want of milk, or having it ſpoyled, ſees her Nurſl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pine away, and (without ume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevention) languiſh till it dyes. The <hi>Palme-tree</hi> is not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from this danger, the Earth which produceth it, in a long tract of time, or by ſome maligne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, growing barren; this defect is communicated to the Tree, which renders it infirme, vitiated, barren till it fails utterly. This diſtemper and indiſpoſition of the Earth, (which the <hi>Palme-tree,</hi> by an attractive virtue ſucks in, with the moyſture that nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, and conveyes throughout from root to head) is diſcovered, by a reddiſh minute ſand, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Earth; The diſeaſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates not onely in the body, but outwardly on the trunck of the Tree; when the <hi>Bandarin</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives this, he is forced through the ſound part of the tree to make
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:57309:53"/>a great hole, to hinder the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious creeping further, as is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctized in Gangrenes, where the ſound part is cut off: the parts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected without, are unbark'd, and where the ſand appears they run in hot Irons. Theſe cures not timely applyed, the profitable tree periſheth.</p>
               <p>Theſe diſaſters are accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a ſecret of Nature, worth reflection. Two or three years before this untimely death, theſe Trees are ſaid to be laden with <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co's</hi> or Nuts, ſo beyond Cuſtome, that this unuſual exceſſe is ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Natives, and awakens them to watch the diſeaſes inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Palmetree, ſo to hinder them by a timely preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Nature by this overplus, ſeems to ſupply the abſence and loſſe of this Tree; and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial Palme, foreſeeing the End of her munificence, ſtrives
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57309:53"/>to recompence her Owner.</p>
               <p>There is yet in the Palmetree a thing more excellent, delicious, more gratefull to the palate, than hath been mentioned; a Morſell to be compared with whatſoever is eſteemed moſt delicate, is that they call Palmito, the innermoſt Eye of the tree; which being cut out and ſtript of the boughes, may paſſe for the Center of all the branches, which in the heart of the Tree, before they ſhoot forth are ſo joyned and united, as to appear the ſame thing. The ſubſtance of this <hi>Palmito</hi> is white like milk, delicious in extreamity, coagulat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, tender, of a taſte above milk, more delightfull and of a better Confection; <hi>in fine a Bocone</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the higheſt, and free from all fulſomeneſſe. What I have ſaid is without exaggeration, the Reader I am ſure, would, if he taſted it, be of my opinion, who
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:57309:54"/>am able to give a ſufficient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this <hi>Palmito,</hi> for beſides my experience of it in <hi>India,</hi> where other proviſion wanted not, at the Cape of good Hope (where the Veſſel, we came in for <hi>Portugal,</hi> ſuffered ſhipwrack, at the land called <hi>Terra de Natal,</hi> and where we ſpent eight months on ſhoar, in the place we were firſt caſt upon, to build two barks to ſave our Company) I had leiſure enough to be convinced of its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſiteneſſe, there ſcarcity of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, obliged us to make uſe of what we found; 'twas our good fortune to light on great ſtore of Palmetrees, not of thoſe which yield <hi>Coco's</hi> or Nuts, but of that ſpecies which bear Dates; there, having known in <hi>India</hi> what the <hi>Palmito</hi> was, we in a ſhort time fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed our ſelves with as many as grew in a leagues compaſſe; the <hi>Palmito</hi> ſerved us for food and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57309:54"/>dainty, neither was its gratefull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hightned by our hunger.</p>
               <p>The Fruitfullneſſe and profit of the Palmetree, laſts many years; there are ſigns for a near gueſſe, at her preciſe duration. This tree puts forth every year four Branches, which leiſurely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play themſelves in the forme of a Croſſe, after three or four years decay; which the Palmetree of her ſelf caſts off, or they are lopt off by the Bandarins, every one leaves a mark where it grew: By theſe is given a probable conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture at the age of the tree. That it may appear how the whole Palmetree is ſerviceable to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane life, nothing ſuperfluous, but all ſubſtantially profitable, from the deepeſt root to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt leaves: The Root (as hath been ſaid before, where we ſpoke of the virtue of the other parts) Chark'd, gives an excellent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:57309:55"/>to Iron; The boughes and leaves, made up with a wick, ſerve for a torch, (called by them <hi>Chuli</hi>) with this Travellers are ſecure from all danger of Serpents, which abound in <hi>India,</hi> are of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite poyſon, and their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude makes them frequent the Roads, and aſſault Paſſengers: They fly from the light of this <hi>Chuli;</hi> of another ſervice when they fiſh in the Rivers, in ſtead of a Candle as is uſual in <hi>Portugal:</hi> Of the leaves beſides, are made great Paraſols, capable to ſhelter two perſons from the Sun or Rain; theſe require a man to carry them (there are perſons deputed for that office) and are called <hi>Boy de Sombrero;</hi> ſmall portable ones there are for the ſame uſe, none walking in the ſtreets, winter or ſummer without great or little Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſols. The leaves have another uſe; of them are made Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57309:55"/>for their Palanquins or Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in which one perſon is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly carried and defended from the rain and ſun. Some Palmetrees afford leaves called <hi>Olhas,</hi> which ſerve for Books and Paper, with a ſmall Iron Pencil in ſtead of a pen, they open and grave the letters, upon the leaf or <hi>Olha,</hi> without the uſe of Inke, as faſt and as eaſily, as the ſwifteſt writer. The leafs of the Tree <hi>Cajuri</hi> dried, remain of a lively white colour, which are made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hatts, of great account though cheap, being ſo becoming, ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately wrought and light, that every body the <hi>vice-roy</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, deſires to wear them: the <hi>Indians</hi> call them <hi>Palhate.</hi> The Bark of the <hi>Poyo</hi> or twig on which grow the fair cluſters of <hi>Coc'os,</hi> being of a thicker and ſtronger ſubſtance furniſh the Common people, particularly the Banderins,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:57309:56"/>who dreſſe the Palmetrees with Caps made like the Engliſh ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Riding-caps.</p>
               <p>To end the diſcourſe, I ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, (what challenges a reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) the natural fabrick of the Palmetree; that the trunk being very ſlender and diſproportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the tallneſſe, the whole weight of the boughes, (called Palmes) and of the fruit, being at the top, in a manner at the verti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal point of the ſlim body, the boughes, as they grow, diſplaying themſelves, and amongſt them hanging the fair cluſters of <hi>Coco's,</hi> the ſhock of winds, ſhould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, eaſily break and ruine this diſproportioned Machin. Provident nature, againſt this, hath for every new birth of thoſe boughes provided ſwathes, of the ſame matter and texture of the Palmetree, not unlike courſe cloath or Canvas: with theſe the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57309:56"/>branches and what grows there, are ſwathed ſo ſtrongly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely as to defy any violence of winds to diſjoynt them: they are liable to be ſhak'd, yet not where they have this Girdle, which to break is a work of Iron. By theſe the Palmetree, as a tender mother, gathers her Children about her, as ſecure from being loſt and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as they are well defended againſt any violence of wind, which would tear and force them from her boſom.</p>
               <p>This is what, for the ſatisfaction of the Curious, could be known of the Palmetree, of what ſpecies ſoever; who deſires a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and ſevere relation, may travell into <hi>India,</hi> and thoſe other parts where this Tree grows, may enquire more minutely, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps looſe his labour.</p>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
